Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Cadet de Vaux, Antoine-Alexis. Paris
    Concerning an account, published by him in Le Journal de Paris, connected with the Mazarin College; obtained M. Dubourg's consent to introduce some things relative to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 17; D.S. 2p.; George Lawder and others
    Parole. Subjects of George III, taken prisoners by the "Black Prince," and granted their discharge on condition that they answer to their names in the expected exchange of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 18; A.L.S. 1p.; St Suice, -----. Passy
    Hopes Franklin will accept the enclosed couplet in his honor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Pellegrini, Joseph. Vienna
    Graduated in medicine at the University of Vienna; had planned to go to America with his fellow-student, Kaufmann, a native of Philadelphia, whose untimely death put on end to these hopes; wishes to know if Franklin can procure him a passage to Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Wiliams, Jonathan Jr. Nantes
    Enclosing Franklin a copy of Arthur Lee's answer to the arbitrators.(XXXVIII, 40a.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Hill, Samuel. Carhaix
    Surgeon on the "Drake" when she was taken by the "Ranger"; begs permission to return to his native country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre, Martinique
    Account of Count d'Estaing's conquest of the island of Grenada and his successful encounter with Lord Byron's fleet; regrets that circumstances prevent the French from attacking St. Kitts; the importance of such an acquisition; what the loss of the West Indies must mean to England; the attitude of Great Britain, the disposition of her troops, etc.; believes, should the war continue, that the West Indies will become a busy theatre of action.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Amcaga, M. d'
    Inquiring if he will dine at home on the following Sunday and if he can see him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 21; A.L.S. 2p.; de Fontfrede, ------. Clermont-Ferrand
    Desires news of his son, who embarked for America under the command of de Coudray; begs Franklin to find out if he still lives.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Gursch, Theodore. Paris
    His service in the armies of the King of Prussia; anxious to offer his services to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Thompson, James. Brest
    Has sent, by Captian Carey, all the letters he brought from Boston; expects to sail for home on the 5th of August, in case Franklin should have any commissions to entrust him with.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Furnishing proof that the privateers complained of by the Spanish Court were not Americans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the exchange of American prisoners for those captured by the "General Mifflin."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Slow progress of his trial; effort of Mr. Lee, by throwing doubt on the Court's authority, to put a stop to the examination; will carry the decision to Franklin in person.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Capt. Foligny, who has just returned from the West Indies, and will be able to give him an account of the naval operations in that part of the world.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 22; A.L.S. 4p.; Cavallier, -----. Palermo
    Desires to give up his prosperous career as a merchant to become a citizen of America and cultivate a little corner of the earth. His friend, T.T.S. Nicoud, also desires to become an American citizen and writes a line to that effect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] July 22; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Postponing a visit to Franklin. Invites him to luncheon on Saturday and promises to dine with him the following day.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Nov., 1906, 173.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Becker and Saltzmann. Berlin
    Offering uniforms and other articles needed in times of war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Martin, Pierre. Livourne
    Believes that Franklin is not ignorant of his family and of their possessions on the other side of the Atlantic; is convinced that the Americans will be ready to restore to the innocent heirs the lands so unjustly seized by the English; if he could count on Franklin's protection and his intercession with Congress, he would embark at once for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Dehez, Bernard. Saint Sebastien
    Concerning the capture by Capt. Conyngham of a French vessel from London, laden with English merchandise; the legal process which ensued; authority invested in him by Capt. Conyngham to defend his side of the case; desires the necessary funds to enable him to see the affair through.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Duchemin, Daniel. Amiens
    At present with his family; unable to accept Franklin's invitation to stay with him, as he is suffering with rheumatism, the result of a wound; has decided not to return to America; begs Franklin to procure for him the sums due him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 23; A.L.S. 1p.; de la Coupe, Pillat. Paris
    Begs him to send the seven bills of exchange forwarded by M. Grand for his acceptance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Lalande, Joseph-Jérôme Le François de, and Barbeau-Dubourg. Paris
    Introducing M. des Raggi, who desires to go to America, and establish a business there. Sorry that the "Lodge of the Nine Sisters" will not be able this year to have their celebration at Passy.
    [Note from M. Dubourg at the close of the above letter, endorsing the recommedation and asking Franklin to procure him if possible a free passage. ]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 23; L.S. 3p.; Wagner, Philippe. Dunkirk
    Desiring an advance of twenty louis to enable him to pay his expenses to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Writes on behalf of the unfortunate American prisoners, recently exchanged; Capt. Babcock willing to give them all ship room, provided they are supplied with clothes, provisions and necessaries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 24; A.L.S. 5p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Outlining the details of a business venture concerning the vessel "La Marquise de Lafayette," which, though bought by the French Government was equipped out of their capital; thinks M. Ray de Chaumont might be able to help him recover the sum, if Franklin should ask his influence in the matter; enclosing an account of the affair in French, addressed to M. de Sartine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Marchant, Capt. Stephen. On board the "Black Prince," Morlaix Road
    His cruise, since setting sail on the 15th inst.; number of sloops and brigs sunk, ransomed and sent to France; number of prisoners brought in; apologizes for their fewness, owing to his lack of men.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779? July 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Paris
    Enclosing parts of the Ledger, which may perhaps contain some news; also a letter from a gentleman of good connection and information in London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Glad to have his authority increased, as it widens his chances of successful enterprises. Promises to send Franklin a cipher for private correspondence; desires that further orders may be sent to the port of his destination by the middle of September.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Blittenberg, —. Paris
    Writes on behalf of his friend, Lewis Dupré who was captured by the English and confined in the prison at Gosport; his subsequent release and safe arrival at Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Jacques Rocquette, T.A. Elsevier, and Fréres Rocquette. Paris
    Enclosing a parcel just received from St. Eustatia, also a letter for Mr. Arthur Lee.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Rayneval, Joseph Gérard de
    Begging Franklin to return him a certain letter relative to the vessel "The Three Friends"; has reason to believe it was despatched without the signature of the Comte de Vergennes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Has received information that the Jamaica fleet will sail homewards, escorted by a fifty gun ship and two strong frigates; should they fall in with this force will certainly engage them; fears, however, that they are not strong enough to prevent the escape of the convoy; asks that the frigate "Monsieur" may be added to his force.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Austin, Jonathan Loring. Boston
    Introducing Mr. William Knox, of Boston, brother of General Knox, who desires to pay his respects to Franklin on his way to Holland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Charles, Gervais. La Rochelle
    Desires to enter into commercial relations with the United States; begs Franklin's recommendation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the examination of his accounts; attitude of the arbitrators.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Raspe, Rudolph Erich. London
    Is neither easy nor happy in a country where low ambition and the pride of kings have driven out virtue and learning; wishes to procure some work abroad.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 28; A.L.S. 3p.; de St Hubert, -----. Caen
    Begging Franklin to subscribe to his "Dictionnaire Topographique, Historique, etc., de la France"; describes the number of volumes, the plan of the work and the proposed date of its completion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Gellée, Nicolas-Maurice. Paris
    The bearer will deliver the key of the apartment he occupied in Franklin's house; has decided to quit a post which circumstances have rendered untenable, and as it would humiliate him to touch the salary, M. Didelot will return the money; apologizes for the scandal caused in Franklin's house by a rascally tailor; reasons why he refused to pay him; intends to leave that night for Berlin; omitted a personal leave-taking for fear of increasing Franklin's displeasure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Thinks it will be necessary to delay the departure of the "Bon Homme Richard," in order to furnish Capt. Jones with a better crew; in this case desires Franklin to order Captain Landais to leave L'Orient at once, in the "Alliance," and cruise to the north of Scotland until the end of September.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 Jan. 28; A.L.S. 3p.; O’Heguerty, Peter Charles Daniel, count. Nancy
    Desires to enter the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Hears that a frigate has just arrived at Brest, which may have brought news from America; begs to be informed of anything which may concern his fellow-citizens. Contradictory reports concerning Charleston; knows not what to believe; evident that Fort la Fayette is taken.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Bon Homme Richard"
    Concerning the court-martial at present in progress; the matter of the "Bon Homme Richard" and the "Alliance" having run foul of each other not yet settled; two quartermasters before the Court, charged with conspiracy at sea; evidence strongly against them; should any person be condemned to death, will suspend the execution of the sentence until the arrival of Franklin's orders. Has sent one of his officers to Nantes in hopes of enlisting a number of Americans who arrived there in the cartel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Diot, John. Morlaix
    Forwarding a journal of all the proceedings of the "Black Prince" during her cruise; account of her prizes and prisoners; begs Franklin to hasten the condemnation of the said prizes. Certificate enclosed [dated August 26, 1779] of certain English prisoners having arrived safely at the prison of Bague.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 29; A.L.S. 3p.; McCraken, John. Morlaix
    Was a passenger on board the "Dublin" when she was taken by the "Black Prince"; is now at liberty to return to Bristol; anxious to rejoin his family there and then embark with them for Pennsylvania; begs Franklin's advice and assistance; is a native of Ireland; mentions various of his relatives in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Concerning Franklin's scheme for aiding Mrs. Mecom; is willing to assist in every possible way. Introducing Col. Watson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Miller, Joseph. Tours
    Commanded the brig "Sampson" when she was taken in August, 1778, by the "Gen. Mifflin"; has been a prisoner ever since; begs that he may be allowed to return to England; never took up arms aganist America; was always in the merchant service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Willams, Jonathan Sr. Boston
    Introducing Mr. Knox, the General's brother.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    At M. la Lande's request, urges Franklin to grant to M. des Raggi his protection that he may embark for America to fight for the country on sea and to serve her on land. Reminds Franklin again of M. Gregoire, a merchant of Havre, who desires a small consulship of agency in the American service. Awaits with eagerness the remainder of Franklin's works, including the " Morals of Chess"; will endeavor to use them to Franklin's satisfaction. Desires to know if he has sure intelligence of the defeat of Gen. Prevost by Gen. Lincoln.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] July 29; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Keay, -----. Paris
    Returning the History of Welsh Poetry, with thanks. Illness of Mme. de Cheminot prevented their waiting on Franklin together.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Temple, E. Boston
    Desiring Franklin to add the necessary address to the enclosed letter and forward it to Mr. [John] Temple.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Lavaysse and Co. L'Orient
    Asking that the commander of the "Alliance" be made to return the ship "The Three Friends," of Dublin, to her owners, together with her cargo in good condition, and also idemnify them for the loss caused by this delay.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 30; A.L.S. 2p.; de Grasslang, Godt. Paris
    Sending a proposition from one of the Swiss cantons to establish a settlement in America; desires to wait upon Franklin and explain the details.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 30; A.L. 3p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Editing of Franklin's works; believes Franklin will not be displeased with what follows his "Aurora Borealis." Desires to know if the Due de Chaulnes ever showed him a letter out of the "Public Advertiser," signed A. B. upon the subject of Wilson's Experiments; the paper contained novelties as well as errors. Sorry to say that Mr. Henly cut his throat; he died in good circumstances. Wishes to know if Franklin wrote a piece on Liberty and Necessity in 1729 or 1739, with a dedication to Truth. People in England refuse to be frightened by the bugbear of an invasion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 30; A.L.S. W[illia]m Vernon, Pres[iden]t. 1p.; The Navy Board, Eastern Department. Boston
    Notice that Samuel [Simon?] Samson, Captain of the "Mercury" packet boat, has been commissioned to carry dispatches to France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 Aug. 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Concerning the prizes taken by Capt. Marchant of the "Black Prince" and their disposition; trouble caused by the delay in their condemnation; the owners so pleased with the execution wrought by this vessel, that they intend to fit out a companion cutter called the "Black Princess," for which they desire a commission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    The Irish brigantine the "Three Friends," taken by the "Alliance," has sunk at her anchors; if the accident arose from carelessness, a courtmartial shall determine what punishment to inflict; in case it is death, he will execute the sentence at sea. The "Bon Homme Richard " only lacks one hundred men to be completely ready for sea.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. L'Orient
    The prize, "The Three Friends," has lately sunk in the harbor; they have obtained permission from the Admiralty to unload her cargo; cause of the accident not yet discovered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival of Capt. Thompson from Boston with the following news: Battle in Carolina on May 17th; the English put to flight; number of dead and wounded; return to New York of the English who had been ravaging Virginia; the American frigates, "Ranger," "Providence," and "Queen of France" sailed the beginning of June to cruise off the entrance to the Chesapeake.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Breton de la Loutière, abbé —. Paris
    Asking permission to present Franklin with his little work on the present war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July ---; A.L.S. 2p.; Lucas, Henry. Cherbourg
    Is a Virginian by birth and was serving as officer on board the brig "Betsey" from Baltimore, when she was taken by the English; his subsequent escape and arrival in France, where, through the kindness of a M. Drouet, he embarked on board a French privateer; M. Drouet offers to join him in the purchase of a privateer, to be called the "Happy Alliance"; waits only for a commission from Franklin to take command of it under the American flag and proceed against the enemy. Enclosing an account of the proposed transaction, written in French by M. Drouet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 after July 28]; A.N. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Inquiring if it is true that Franklin has parted with M. Gellée, his secretary, and if he requires one to replace him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779] July?; A.L.S. 3p.; John de Neufville and Son
    Their worthy friend, M. Dumas, the bearer of this letter; saw the plan of which he was the bearer; glad to defer to his intercession as regards the proposed loan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 1; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Petrie, S. Paris
    Is about to set forth with two friends on a tour through Flanders; begs Franklin to favor them with a pass.
    Memorandum inserted that Mr. Wharton told Dr. Franklin on August 5th that Mr. Petrie had gone to meet William Lee.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 2; A.L.S. 2p.; St. Firmin, — de. Paris
    Has received a commission as first lieutenant of volunteers on board the "Brave Normand" with the understanding that he was to join his troop at Caen; an illness of fifteen days has absorbed all his little money and he desires a loan to enable him to reach Caen before the ship sails.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de. L'Orient
    Concerning the expulsion of the English from the "Bon Homme Richard" and the substitution of Americans and Portuguese; if Franklin has any orders for Capt. Jones, desires him to send them at once.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Palmer, I. Germantown
    Has just heard of Mr. Adams's arrival in Boston, and also that the fleet and army sent to Penobscot to dislodge the enemy had captured seven or eight hundred land forces, six or eight men-of-war and had driven the enemy up the river. This letter will be handed Franklin by the writer's nephew, Joseph Palmer, who, having finished his studies at Harvard College, is returning to his father, near Plymouth, in England; begs Franklin to advise the young man in all things necessary for his passage to Plymouth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 3; A.L. 4p.; -----, -----. Brussels
    Thinking of settling in Pennsylvania. Could bring many good colonists, artisans and farmers from the country about Liege. Wishes to know what advantages would be offered to them and how they would be provided for on the journey and on their arrival.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Hears that Gen. Knox's brother is expected shortly in France; hopes Franklin will direct him to his (la Fayette's) address. Rumor of Gen. Washington's army being very strong, and of Gen. Sullivan's having gone into Canada; would be glad to have this report confirmed. They are now ready to embark, but M. d'Orvillier's fleet has not yet been heard of.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Taylor, Cradock. Aix
    Hard that he should be kept a prisoner in France when he is a native of Virginia and a subject of the United States; would never have gone on board a British sloop of war, had he not been betrayed into it by the showing of the American colors; begs for an early answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Brice?, John. Aix
    Writes again to beg Franklin to procure him his liberty, that he may use it in defense of his country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Auer, M Deacon. Ebingen near Bahlingen, Württemberg
    States that son of widow Anne Catharine Höcklerin went to Pennsylvania and worked for her brother-in-law, Christian Schneider, a tanner in Germantown, and saved some money. Her son died three year ago. Schneider desires to send her the money he left, but fears for its safety in these troubled times.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Auer, M Deacon. Ebingen near Bahlingen, Württemberg
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 4; A.L.S. 1p.; La Faye, Julien-Pierre de. Paris
    Begs Franklin to listen to the proposition which Madame du Lin is entrusted to make to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Poullin, -----. Nantes
    Reminding him of a promise of letters of recommendation whenever he should be ready to embark for America; expects to sail about the 14th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 6; A.L.S. 6p.; Besson, Leopold George. Montbéliard
    Is paralyzed and without means; begs Franklin to contribute towards his support.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Lovell, James. Philadelphia
    Franklin's favor of July 22, 1778, never came to hand until the 31st of July, 1779. Concerning the fight between Messrs. Deane and Lee; thinks the former wrecked himself upon the quicksands of indiscretion, and that his publication of December 5th totally ruined his claims to any public trust; admits that Congress was misled in the case of Mr. Lee, but does not think it follows that they should destroy an able and faithful servant.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 August 6; A.L.S. 2p.; A.L.S. 2p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Expressing the greatest astonishment at not hearing from Franklin for more than twelve months. Begs leave to trouble him with a few more circular letters of Bache and Shee, and asks for the names of the houses to whom their letters are sent. Congratulates him on Count d'Estaing's successes in the West Indies.
    (Two Copies.)
    P. S. August 9. Concerning a sum he sent to Mr. Williams to be laid out in various articles for Sally's and the family's use; considerable inconvenience caused by their non-arrival.